<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arraignment of unbelief, as the grand cause of our nationall non-establishment: cleared in a sermon to the Honourable House of Commons in Parliament, at Margarets Westminster, upon the 28th. of May, 1645. being the day of their publike fast. / By Joseph Caryl, late preacher to the Honourable Society of Lincolnes-Inne, now pastor at Magnus neer the bridge, London.</title>
            <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E286_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860879</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860879</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E286[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arraignment of unbelief, as the grand cause of our nationall non-establishment: cleared in a sermon to the Honourable House of Commons in Parliament, at Margarets Westminster, upon the 28th. of May, 1645. being the day of their publike fast. / By Joseph Caryl, late preacher to the Honourable Society of Lincolnes-Inne, now pastor at Magnus neer the bridge, London.</title>
                  <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Miller for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLV. [1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah VII, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158527:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARRAIGNMENT OF UNBELIEF, AS The Grand Cauſe of Our Nationall Non-eſtabliſhment: Cleared in a SERMON to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> in PARLIAMENT, at <hi>Margarets Westminster,</hi> upon the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>May,</hi> 1645. being the Day of their Publike Faſt.</p>
            <p>By JOSEPH CARYL, late Preacher to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Society of <hi>Lincolnes-Inne,</hi> now Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor at <hi>Magnus</hi> neer the Bridge, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 78. Ver. 32, 33.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For all this they ſinned ſtill, and beleeved not for his wondrous works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore their daies did he conſume in vanity, and their years in trouble.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Miller</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> M. DC. XLV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:158527:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in PARLIAMENT, that Sir <hi>Robert Harley</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> do from this Houſe give thanks to M. <hi>Caryl</hi> and M. <hi>Ford,</hi> for the great pains they took in the Sermons they preached this day at the intreaty of this Houſe at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Margarets Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (it being the day of Publike humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation) and to deſire them to Print their Sermons; And they are to have the like priviledge in printing of them, as others in the like kinde uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 5. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I appoint <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:158527:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Honourable the Houſe of Commons Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was called by <hi>your voice</hi> to prepare <hi>this Sermon,</hi> your affairs were much unſetled, and ſo were the hearts of moſt about them. This (beſides the everlaſting uſefullneſſe of the ſubject) was one ſpeciall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive leading me to this Text and theſe Meditations; It hath pleaſed God, ſince that, to ſhine very graciouſly upon your <hi>Counſels,</hi> and to proſper <hi>Thoſe Heroes</hi> who act abroad by your Orders and Authority, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing ſucceſſes: which raiſe this hope, that God inſtead of puniſhing, is healing our <hi>unbelief;</hi> as alſo that (poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly) this Sermon hath had (through his bleſsing) a hand in helping on the cure. When the woman touched Chriſt by faith, he quickly perceived that vertue was gone out of him: while we cannot but perceive that
<pb facs="tcp:158527:3"/> much vertue is gone out from Chriſt, in giving our late Victories; may we not conclude, that ſome body hath touched him? Faith may juſtly be ſirnamed <hi>Long-hand,</hi> it can reach to Heaven. And one battell wonne by the hand of faith reaching Heaven, is more glorious then a thouſand by an earthly naked ſword. We read <hi>(Num.</hi> 21. 14.) of an ancient record (of which there are now no remains but that mention) whoſe Title-page, is, <hi>The Book of the warres of the Lord.</hi> And why the warres of the Lord? Surely, becauſe the Lord engaged for his people in thoſe warres. What ever elſe may, the actings of holy faith will engage the Lord. Act faith, and then the records of theſe times (on your ſide) ſhall bear thus to all poſterity, <hi>The Book of the warres and counſels of the Lord.</hi> If theſe words preached have had, or print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall yet give any advantage toward ſuch a <hi>Title of your Acts and Monuments,</hi> in the great work of our <hi>Nationall eſtabliſhment,</hi> you have the deſires and ends, which lye next to the <hi>glory of God,</hi> in the heart of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sirs,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble ſervant in the work of the Lord,</hi> Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Erratum.</hi> pag. 38. lin. 15. <hi>for</hi> proofs <hi>read</hi> reproofs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158527:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED To the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>May,</hi> 1645. the day of their ſolemn monethly Faſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISA. 7. 9. the latter part of the verſe.</bibl>
               <q>If ye will not beleeve, ſurely ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the beginning of this Chapter we read a warre prepared, and a ſtrong confederacie entred againſt <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem: It was told the houſe of David, ſaying, Syria is confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with Ephraim,</hi> ver. 2. It is worth our conſideration, who were joyned in confederacie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom; <hi>Syria and Ephraim,</hi> are confederate againſt <hi>Judah.</hi> The <hi>Syrians</hi> were profeſt enemies to the Jewes, they had no civil relation to them, and their religion was at furtheſt diſtance: but <hi>Ephraim</hi> was near to <hi>Judah,</hi> both in religion and civill relation; and yet <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> (that is, the revolted ten Tribes) ioyn together, and mingle their forces and counſels to invade <hi>Judah,</hi> who held forth the true worſhip of God. Whence note,</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:158527:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>That mungrell corrupt profeſſors of true religion, will joyn with open enemies, againſt thoſe who are zealous and faithfull profeſsors of true religion.</hi> We ſee at this day <hi>Syria</hi> confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with <hi>Ephraim,</hi> looſe libertine Proteſtants mixt with Papiſts, againſt thoſe who are cloſe-covenanting, and cloſe-walking Proteſtants. And there is a clear reaſon for it; corrupt hearts ſeek their own eaſe, and therefore will eaſier joyn with thoſe who are more looſe, then with thoſe who are more ſtrict then themſelves: Aſcents and improvements in holineſſe pinch corruption; nature had rather go backward, then come onne in religion, and thinks we have gone beyond all reproof, if we keep pace with our fore-fathers, and tread in their ſteps.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Syria is confederate with Ephraim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This report being brought to <hi>Ahaz</hi> the King of <hi>Iudah, his heart was moved, and the heart of his people, as the trees of the wood are moved with the winde.</hi> We are ready to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, as the ſinfull actions, ſo the paſſions of Princes; when Magiſtrates and Leaders are afraid, the people ſeldome take courage. <hi>His heart was moved, and the heart of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> All <hi>Iudah</hi> ſhakes from head to foot, they ſhake within as well as without, <hi>their hearts were moved.</hi> The heart (as Aſtronomers tell us of the higheſt ſphere,) is the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> the firſt mover, whoſe motion turns all the ſpheres of this leſſer world (man) If the heart be moved with fear, all the members of the body move with fear; if the heart be moved with joy, all the members of the body move with joy: This <hi>moved-heart</hi> is oppoſed to a <hi>fixed-heart</hi> (Pſal. 112. 7.) <hi>his heart is fixed.</hi> The heart is like <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver,</hi> if you can fix that, you have fixed all; if that flee, all flees.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:158527:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>His heart was moved, and the heart of his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they were in this fit and feaver of fear, ſhaking at the very heart, behold the goodneſſe of God <hi>(ver.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.) <hi>Then ſaid the Lord unto Iſaiah, Go forth now to meet Ahaz, and ſay unto him; Take heed, and be quiet, fear not.</hi> Two things I will note from this, in paſſage.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God is acquainted, not only with our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſtractions and troubles, but with our inward fears and perturbations. He knows the ſtirrings of every heart: if your hearts do but pant at any danger, the Lord ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it. And then.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That as ſoon as the Lord ſees a wound in the ſpirits of his people, he preſently provides a Phyſician, and ſends a plaiſter. As ſoon as ever it was ſaid, their hearts were moved, God raiſeth up his Prophet, and puts a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reviving word in his mouth to ſtrengthen and ſettle them again: <hi>Go forth now to meet Ahaz, and ſay unto him, Take heed, and be quiet, fear not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As the Lord gives them counſell not to fear, ſo he ſhewes them reaſon why they ſhould not. Firſt, from the perſons who appeared ſo dreadfull, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>They are but two tails of ſmoaking firebrands.</hi> As if he had ſaid, You look upon theſe men as a devouring fire, or unquenchable flames; but I aſſure you they do but ſmoak, and they are but brands, and they are but tayls of brands, they have almoſt conſumed themſelves; they are but brands ends, and they are ſmoaking rather then burning. As that phraſe in the Goſpel, <hi>ſmoaking flax,</hi> notes the loweſt degree of grace which Jeſus Chriſt will not quench or put out: ſo here, <hi>ſmoaking firebrands,</hi> note the leaſt degree of remaining power, or malice almoſt ſpent and going out,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158527:5"/> not in regard of deſires, but abilities to do miſchief.</p>
            <p>Again, As the Lord ſhewes their power, ſo neer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct that they could do no great hurt; ſo he declares his own will that they ſhould not, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord, It ſhall not ſtand, neither ſhall it come to paſſe.</hi> Ther's no reaſon we ſhould run for fear, when we are aſſured the counſels of our enemies ſhall not ſtand: They are confederate, but they ſhall be broken: they have taken counſel, but <hi>it ſhall not ſtand, neither ſhall it come to paſse. The counſels of men ſtand or fall at the pleaſure of God.</hi> The oppoſition of all creatures cannot hinder one of his counſels, and all their endeavours cannot produce one of their own. Though a conclave of <hi>Achitophels</hi> (every one an Oracle) ſhould lay a deſign, yet it is at the will of God whether it ſhall ſucceed. <hi>The policie of man is no match for God:</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>it ſhall not stand.</hi> Not ſtand! why? who is able to throw it down? by whoſe hand ſhall it fall? <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> are mighty in power, as well as deep in policie, ſhall their counſels be made voide? The Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> knowing the weakneſſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions <hi>(chap.</hi> 7. 2.) <hi>By whom ſhall Jacob ariſe, for he is ſmall?</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> knowing the ſtrength of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Ephraim,</hi> might queſtion, By whom ſhall theſe fall, for they are great? Yes, ſaith God, I aſſure you how great ſo ever they are, they ſhall not ſtand; I can reckon up the greateſt of their ſtrength, and the top of their confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>The head of Syria</hi> (that is, the chief power and ſtrength of <hi>Syria) is Damaſcus</hi> (the mother City) <hi>and the head of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus is Rezin</hi> (the King of <hi>Syria) and in threeſcore and five yeers ſhall Ephraim be broken that it be not a people; And the head of Ephraim is Samaria</hi> (I can tell you likewiſe what ſtrength <hi>Ephraim</hi> hath, and who is the ſtrongeſt perſon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158527:5"/> there) <hi>The head of Samaria is Remaliahs ſonne:</hi> I can ſoon caſt up all the power of your enemies, I can go to the very head of it, it is but <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and <hi>Rezin,</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Remaliahs</hi> ſonne, this is the outſide of their ſtrength. We may quickly ſee an end of all worldly perfections, both in power and policie. Now, that which is ſecretly implied and couched in this contemptuous account of <hi>Ephraims</hi> and <hi>Syrias</hi> ſtrength, is, that <hi>Iudah</hi> had ſuch a head, as they were not able to reach, ſuch forces as they were not able to tell over, much leſſe to triumph over. It is as if he had ſaid, You ſee the head of <hi>Syria,</hi> and the head of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> but the head of <hi>Iudah</hi> is <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the head of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is Jeſus Chriſt: Who is able to reach the head of <hi>Iudah,</hi> which is <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> while that hath Jeſus Chriſt for the head of it? who is <hi>Rezin,</hi> or <hi>Remaliahs</hi> ſon, put into the balance with Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>The Prophet having brought them this meſſage, not to fear, and ſtrengthened it with theſe reaſons, concludes all with an Epiphonema, in the words of the text, <hi>If ye will not beleeve, ſurely ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed:</hi> As if he had ſaid, I have brought you as good newes as you can deſire, ſhould the Lord have ſent you down a blank from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and bid you write the wiſhes of your own hearts in this condition, and engag'd his own faithfullneſſe and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency to performe them, what could you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted that I have not offered? could you frame any more ſutable mercies, as your caſe ſtands, then theſe? that your enemies ſhall fall, that their counſels ſhall not ſtand, that their projects ſhall not come to paſſe? yet let me tell you, ye may obſtruct theſe bleſſings, and deprive your ſelves of this promiſed deliverance; your unbelief may weaken the arm of your ſalvation, and re-inkindle theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158527:6"/> ſmoaking brands into a conſuming flame; your unbelief may ſhake your kingdome, more then your feares have hitherto ſhakt your hearts, <hi>If ye beleeve not, ſurely ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are diverſly read: The margin of our Bibles gives them thus out of the Hebrew; <hi>Do ye not beleeve?</hi> it is, <hi>becauſe ye are not ſtable:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay; What! after the report of theſe gracious promiſes, do ye perſiſt in your fear ſtill? are you yet in your trembling fit? ye are unbeleeving ſure, and therefore ye are unſtable. An un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving heart, muſt needs be (when put to it) a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling heart.</p>
            <p>The Septuagint give us another ſenſe; <hi>If ye beleeve not, ye ſhall not underſtand:</hi> according to which tranſlation, the text is often cited by the Ancients, to prove that the <hi>Iewes</hi> did not therefore underſtand the Scripture, becauſe they did not beleeve: faith is the light, as well as the ſtrength of the ſoul; and they who are ſhut up in unblief, are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhut up in ignorance: Our reading ſutes the Prophets meſſage, and bears fair with the Grammaticall conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the text, <hi>If ye will not beleeve, ſurely ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed:</hi> though ye have heard of much good, you ſhall not taſte a drop of it; though God hath infinite ſtrength for you, yet he will not put forth the leaſt of it, except ye beleeve. There is an elegant Paronomaſia <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>phil</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it, in n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phal, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, ſtatum eſſe.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in the Originall: That word which in the active Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſignifies to beleeve, ſignifies to be eſtabliſhed in the paſſive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye beleeve not.]</hi> Unbelief is of two ſorts; either, firſt, an impotencie or inability to beleeve; or ſecondly, a crookedneſſe or perverſeneſſe of diſpoſition againſt the means of beleeving: underſtand this text of the latter.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158527:6"/> Again, unbelief may be taken either in generall, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the whole revealed will of God; or ſecondly, in particular, in reference to ſome ſpeciall manifeſtation of it. The Jewes, to whom the Prophet here ſpeaks, were all beleevers in the former notion, but many of them proved unbeleevers in the latter; even as on the other hand, the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> who were unbeleevers, in reſpect of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall word, proved beleevers, in regard of that ſpeciall revelation by the Prophet <hi>Ionah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surely ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed:]</hi> That is, ye, in your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike capacity, as a Kingdome and Commonwealth, ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Two points ariſe from the words; the firſt I ſhall but touch in generall: take it thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſes of mercy from God include mans duty,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Acts of ſpirituall duty, and acts of corporall and civill duty. Deliverance and eſtabliſhment are promiſed to King <hi>Ahaz</hi> and his people; but they cannot enjoy ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except they beleeve. The Lord made glorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes for the reſtauration of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and concludes them all with this aſſeveration, <hi>I the Lord have ſpoken it, and I will do it</hi> (Ezek. 36. 36.) nevertheleſſe he adds <hi>(ver.</hi> 37.) <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, I will yet, for this, be enquired of by the houſe of Iſrael to do it for them.</hi> What the Lord will do, we muſt beleeve he will do, and we muſt pray that he would do it: Theſe are acts of ſpirituall duty. And theſe are not all, when the Lord promiſes, we muſt not only ſet our hearts awork to beleeve and pray, but we muſt ſet our hands awork, to labour and do.</p>
            <p>While <hi>Iacob</hi> was travelling to <hi>Padan-aram,</hi> the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to him in a viſion at <hi>Bethel,</hi> and thus encourages him: <hi>Behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee in all places</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:158527:7"/> 
               <hi>whither thou goest, and will bring thee again into this land; for I will not leave thee, till, I have done all that I have ſpoken to thee of,</hi> Gen. 28. 15. And when upon the diſcourteous u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of his uncle <hi>Laban,</hi> he meditated a departure from him; the Lord gives him his Paſſe-port <hi>(ch.</hi> 31. 2) <hi>Return unto the land of thy fathers, and I will be with thee.</hi> How might <hi>Iacob</hi> at the appearance of any danger have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe promiſes, and reſted under the ſhadow of them for protection? Lord, I have thy word, ſurer then the foundations of Heaven and earth, for my ſafety; unleſſe thy truth, or thy power fail, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miſcarry; let <hi>Eſau</hi> threaten and muſter all his forces againſt me, let earth and hell enter league and aſſociate themſelves againſt me; here I ſit under the banner of thoſe gracious promiſes which thou haſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played over me; I will not trouble my ſelf, Lord, thou ſtandeſt charg'd to keep me from all anoyance. But doth <hi>Iacob</hi> make this uſe of the promiſe? Nothing leſſe. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, but he is not careleſſe; he truſts in God, but he neglects not himſelf; though God had ſaid, <hi>I will keep thee whither ſoever thou goeſt,</hi> yet he labours to keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; read, how upon the approach of his bloudy brother, he ſends preſents to appeaſe him, how he divides his flocks and family, to make reſiſtance or eſcape him. That of <hi>Paul (Acts</hi> 27.) is eminent to this purpoſe; where, with his weather-beaten companions in that voyage, having been in great ſtreſſe at ſea, he ſteps forth <hi>(ver.</hi> 22.) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive their fainting ſpirits, with a comfortable meſſage; <hi>Be of good cheer, for there ſhall be no loſſe of any mans life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, but of the ſhip; For there ſtood by me this night the Angel of the Lord, whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve, ſaying; Fear not, Paul, thou must be brought before Caeſar; and lo, God</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:158527:7"/> 
               <hi>hath given thee all thoſe that ſail with thee. Pauls</hi> faith clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes fully with this promiſe <hi>(ver.</hi> 25.) <hi>I beleeve God, that it ſhall be even as he hath told me:</hi> Yet at the 31 verſe, when the ſhip-men, under colour of caſting out Anchors, were about to eſcape in the cock-boat, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion and the Souldiers, <hi>except theſe abide in the ſhip, ye cannot be ſaved;</hi> Not ſaved, <hi>Paul!</hi> where then is the word and promiſe of thy God, upon which thou didſt even now ſo confidently pronounce ſafety to us all? If we run out of the way of God, we run out of the word of God: To rely upon the word, and then go out of the way of God, is not faith, but preſumption: Providence will not ſerve our negligence, neither will the promiſe keep us, except we keep the condition of the promiſe: <hi>If ye beleeve not, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</hi> Obſerve ſecondly;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Without beleeving there is no eſtabliſhing: Vnbelief is a barre in the way of promiſed bleſsings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I (ſaith the Prophet) have made you large promiſes, but take heed ye do not ſtraiten the hand of God, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out the mercy promiſed. As faith ſtops the ſevereſt threatnings of deſtruction, ſo unbelief ſtops the ſweeteſt promiſes of deliverance. <hi>Jonah</hi> propheſies <hi>(chap.</hi> 3. 4.) <hi>Yet fourty daies, and Nineveh ſhall be overthrown;</hi> but the faith of <hi>Nineveh</hi> overthrew that prophecie; the City ſtood, and the prophecie fell; Why? <hi>The people of Nineveh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved God, and proclaimed a faſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. What faith can do to a prophecie of judgement, the ſame can unbelief to a promiſe of mercy, overthrow it.</p>
            <p>The Pſalmiſt aſſignes this to the unbelief of the works of God, as well as of his word <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 78. 32, 33.) They beleeved not his wondrous works, therefore their daies did he conſume in vanity, and their years in trouble. But
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158527:8"/> are not the daies of all men conſumed in vanity? Is not man at his beſt eſtate altogether vanity? Yes: but here was a ſpeciall vanity, and ſomewhat more poenall and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall lay upon that generation, for their unbelief, then lies upon man-kinde, as the fruit of ſinne in generall. And what was that? even the evil threatned in the text; they could not be eſtabliſhed: God lets them wander fourty years in a wilderneſſe, up and down, forward and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, now in hope, anon in fear; now in joy, anon in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; now a ſucceſſe, by and by a diſappointment. They looked for <hi>Canaan,</hi> but to <hi>Canaan</hi> they could not come; they looked for a ſetled condition, but God kept them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on uncertainties; they went toyling about the wilderneſſe to ſeek a paſſage out, yet moſt of them found none, but at the door of the grave: this was the ſpending of their years in vanity; and they ſpent them thus, becauſe of their unbelief. The land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was ſo much promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Iſraelites, that it was called the land of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, yet unbelief kept them out fourty years. The Apoſtle is as plain <hi>(Heb.</hi> 3. 19.) <hi>So we ſee, they could not enter in, becauſe of unbelief:</hi> Their unbelief built a wall between them and <hi>Canaan;</hi> it locked up the paſſages ſo faſt, that they could not enter in. And as it blockt up the way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the unbeleeving Iſraelites, ſo againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and conductor of Iſrael:</hi> he muſt deliver up his <hi>leading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff,</hi> and reſign his <hi>Commiſsion</hi> to his ſervant <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> he muſt die on this ſide <hi>Iordan:</hi> The reaſon is given <hi>(Numb.</hi> 20. 12.) <hi>And the Lord ſpake unto Moſes and Aaron, ſaying, Becauſe ye beleeve me not, to ſanctifie me in the eies of the children of Iſrael; therefore ye ſhall not bring this Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the land which I have given them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Ieremiah (chap.</hi> 17. 5.) pronounceth a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158527:8"/> curſe upon the man, <hi>that truſteth upon man, and maketh fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle expounds whoſe heart that is <hi>(Heb.</hi> 3. 12.) <hi>Take heed leſt there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God.</hi> An unbeleeving heart, is an heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from the living God. The antitheſis in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>(ver.</hi> 7.) confirmes that expoſition; <hi>Bleſsed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is.</hi> Hope and truſt are the contraries to unbelief. But what is the portion of this unbeleeving heart? No good I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you. The ſixth verſe aſſures us ſo, <hi>He ſhall be like the heath in the deſert, and ſhall not ſee when good commeth.</hi> As unbelief locks ſinne upon our ſouls, ſorrows and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon our bodies, ſo it locks our ſouls out of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and our bodies out of temporall ſalvation. An unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever ſhall not ſee when good cometh, that is, he ſhall not taſte or enjoy good when it commeth. So <hi>Eliſha</hi> told that unbeleeving Lord, when in the name of the Lord he had promiſed plenty in <hi>Samaria; Behold, thou ſhalt ſee it with thine eies, but ſhalt not eat thereof,</hi> 2 King. 7. 2.</p>
            <p>That text of the Apoſtle carries a ſhew of oppoſition againſt this truth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 32. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath concluded them all (ſc.</hi> Jews and Gentiles) <hi>in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all:</hi> It ſeems then that mercy rather comes in then is ſhut out by unbelief. God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all, as if God intended to make his advantage and opportunity of ſhewing mercy to that people, by finding them in an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving condition.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; There is a two-fold mercy; Firſt, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of vocation; Secondly, the mercy of ſalvation; when the Apoſtle ſaith, that God concluded or ſhut them all up
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158527:9"/> in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon them all, he means it of the mercy of vocation: The Gentiles in their time, were all unbeleevers, then God called them; and the Jews at this time are unbeleevers, they deny obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpell, yet God will call them again; the calling of the Jews hereafter (as heretofore the calling of the Gentiles) ſhall be of free grace; there was no prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the one, there ſhall be none in the other, to move God to call them to the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt. God calls us to faith, when we have no faith: He calls to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, while we are in unbelief: The mercy of vocation prevents faith; God doth not call men becauſe they are beleevers, or becauſe they have faith, but he calleth them to beleeve, he calleth them unto faith. So the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle arguing about that great mercy of juſtification <hi>(Rom.</hi> 3. 19.) ſhewes how the Lord ſtops every mouth, and makes all the world become guilty before him. God doth not juſtifie any perſon becauſe he is guiltleſſe or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but that he may be guiltleſſe and holy: He doth not juſtifie any man becauſe he is free from ſinne, but that he may be free from ſinne. Thus the mercy of vocation prevents our faith, and the mercy of juſtification prevents our righteouſneſſe and obedience: <hi>God juſtifies the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> But in giving the mercy of ſalvation, whether it be temporall or eternall ſalvation, God looks upon a people or a perſon beleeving; and therefore makes promiſes for faith to act upon, that we may be ſaved, that we may be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>A ſecond objection riſes againſt this point, from that ſpeech of Chriſt, in the cloſe of the Parable of the unjuſt Judge and the importunate Widow, where aſſuring his elect who cry unto him night and day, that he will avenge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158527:9"/> them ſpeedily, he adds, <hi>Nevertheleſſe, when the Sonne of man commeth, ſhall he finde faith on the earth?</hi> that is, he ſhall not finde faith on the earth: and yet then he comes upon a gracious deſign, the deliverance of his elect; It ſeems then that unbelief or want of faith, doth not hinder mercy, for this great mercy ſhall be given in, when faith ſhall not be found to beleeve it: See here a plentifull harveſt of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and yet at the ſame time a dearth of faith; none to be found upon the earth.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, firſt, The words import only a great declining of faith in thoſe times, not a totall decay of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The intent of thoſe words is not to bring unbelief into any credit, but only to ſupport and cheriſh the faith of ſome few, in the appearing of much unbelief and deſpondencie in others: For in hard times we hear frequently ſuch complaints as theſe: <hi>Do ye not ſee, how the hearts of men fail, how their ſpirits are down, how they give up all for lost? Faith was never ſo low as now, and therefore ſurely we muſt ſhortly be lower then we are; this prevailing raign of unbelief among us, is a ſad argument that evils ſhall raign over us too: thus the heart miſgives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To releeve ſuch, our Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Nevertheleſſe, when the Sonne of man comes, ſhall he finde faith on the earth?</hi> As if he had ſaid, though all ought to encreaſe and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then faith in darkeſt times, both in themſelves and others, yet let no man deſpair, becauſe ſome, or many do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve: for as their unbelief ſhall not make the faith (that is, the faithfullneſſe or faith-word) of God without effect <hi>(Rom.</hi> 3. 3.) ſo neither ſhall it make the faith of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men without effect. Yea, in this ſenſe, <hi>the leſse faith, the more hope.</hi> When you ſee the ſpirits of moſt drooping, their fleſh trembling, and their hands hanging down;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158527:10"/> This looks moſt like the time wherein Chriſt will come to avenge his elect, and do great things. And thoſe Saints, in whom faith bears up its head in ſuch times, may uſe the generall unbelief of their brethren, as a ſtrong advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for their own faith; and repreſenting it to God in prayer, may plead thus, Lord, faith failes exceedingly, very few of thy oppreſſed people do, or can be perſwaded to beleeve that thou wilt help them; why, therefore Lord haſten in help now, come to our ſuccour; Is not this the day of thy comming? for thou ſhalt ſcarce finde faith on the earth to beleeve thou wilt come.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though Chriſt will come at laſt to releeve his people, when little faith is to be found among them, yet it ſhall be beſt with thoſe in whom he findes moſt faith: and wo to thoſe who neglect the raiſing of their faith, becauſe they hear Chriſt will come when faith is down. The freeneſſe of his grace, in helping an unbeleeving ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, will be no excuſe, but a reproof of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. Our duty to beleeve is not the leſſe, becauſe his goodneſſe to thoſe who beleeve not, is ſo great: yea, they who (to put themſelves into a poſture for deliverance) caſt away their faith, are cloathed with preſumption: And though Chriſt may eſtabliſh thoſe who, through weakneſſe or want of faith, cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, yet ſurely they ſhall never be eſtabliſhed, who, through boldneſſe with, or wantonneſſe upon his grace, ſtrive not to give him glory in beleeving.</p>
            <p>To cleer which, I ſhall now proceed to give you ſome demonſtrations of this point, why unbelief is the barre and ſtop of bleſſings. This appears;</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the greatneſſe of the ſinne of unbelief; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſinne, in the nature of it, is a barre in the way of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158527:10"/> mercy, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. 25. <hi>Your iniquities have turned away theſe things, and your ſinnes have withholden good things from you.</hi> But unbelief is a huge mountain, and when once we have removed the mountain of unbelief, all other mountains will quickly become plains and vallies before us. Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is a ſinne of a very high ſtature; a ſinne of the firſt magnitude; it is a ſpirituall wickedneſſe, and therefore a great wickedneſſe. There is much diſpute among the learned, whether unbelief were not the firſt ſinne, that which opened the door to let in every ſinne? I beleeve we ſhall not wrong unbelief, in giving it precedencie, or in affirming, that as unbelief now ſhuts the door, and keeps out mercy; ſo unbelief opened the door, to let in miſery upon the world: it was faith, reſpecting the threatning of God, which the Devil laid his firſt ſiege againſt, and againſt which he firſt prevailed: Man had never eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the forbidden fruit, had he beleeved death was in the morſell. Hence unbelief is called a <hi>provocation:</hi> To be provoked, is more then to be diſpleaſed: Provocation notes the higheſt act of diſpleaſure, and therefore that ſinne which is a provocation, is one of the higheſt ſinnes. A day of unbelief is a day of provocation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, in the day of tentation in the wilderneſſe.</hi> Now what was the provocation of that day? or by what did the people provoke God at that time? Was it the making of a molten Calf, and falling down before it? Was it the joyning themſelves unto <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> and eating the offerings of the dead? Was adultery or uncleneneſſe acted in the day of that provocation? All theſe are provoking ſinnes, yet none of theſe denominated that day, a day of provocation; unbelief gave the name to that day: For the Iſraelites provoked God at the red ſea
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158527:11"/> 
               <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 106. 7.) and that was before they made their idol calfe to worſhip it, and before they fell into thoſe bodily abominations and defiled themſelves; their fear and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings ſtoried <hi>(Exod.</hi> 14.) were but the overflowings of their unbelief, and theſe provoked God at the red ſea.</p>
            <p>Again, The greatneſſe of the ſinne appears, from the many proviſions which God hath made againſt it. God hath even ſtudied the prevention, or the cure of this ſinne: He hath appointed faith, many helps, much aſſiſtance, he hath prepared many antidotes againſt, many remedies for unbelief. Now look how much the more proviſion God makes to keep us off, or pull us out of any ſinne, by ſo much the greater is that ſinne, if we fall into, or continue in it. When God gives many charges againſt a ſinne, and ſets many barres in the way to ſtop us from it, and yet we break thorow all, this mightily aggravates a ſinne, and makes it out of meaſure ſinfull. For the cure of unbelief, we have not only the Word of God; but ſecondly, the Promiſe of God; and thirdly, the Covenant of God; and fourthly, the Oath of God; fiftly, all elder and later ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, the mighty works which God hath done, the ſignes which he hath given, the wonders and miracles which he hath wrought. Hence, after Chriſt had preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and done many wondrous works among his country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it is ſaid, <hi>Mark.</hi> 6. 6. that <hi>he marvelled at the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Iews: unbelief is a marvellous ſinne,</hi> and, which makes it moſt marvellous, Chriſt marvelled at it. We read not that Chriſt marvelled at any other ſinne of that generation; he marvelled not at their adulteries, or oaths, or hypocriſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> why then doth he marvell at their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief? Not becauſe it is a ſinne above, or beſides the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, nor becauſe it was a rare ſinne, a ſinne he had
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:158527:11"/> not ſeen before (Unbelief is as levell to our ſinfull nature, and as daily acted, as any ſin whatſoever) The reaſon then of this marvell, was, the ſtrange courſe which thoſe men ran, and all do, in acting their unbelief: They over-run and ſleight the word of God, the promiſe of God, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God, the Oath of God, all the works, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, marvels and miracles of God; is not this a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſinne which breaks thorow all theſe? Laſtly, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief is a very great ſin, for, it is the mother of moſt ſins, and the ſweetner of every ſinne; many ſinnes had never ſeen the light, and all ſinne would be gall and worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, bitterneſſe in the acting, did man beleeve it would be (as it will be) bitterneſſe in the end: Unbelief gilds over that poiſonous pill, and wraps it up in ſugar, and ſo man takes it down as a ſweet bit, as pleaſant bread, with death, and hell and all.</p>
            <p>If then a great ſinne be a barre to bleſſings, unbelief muſt; which was in order the firſt ſinne, which is in kinde a ſpirituall ſinne, in degree one of the greateſt ſinnes, a provoking ſinne, a marvellous ſinne, a mother ſinne, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Unbelief is a ſtop in the way of bleſſing and eſtabliſhment, becauſe it diverts us from the fountain of bleſſings, from him who only can eſtabliſh, from him who bears up the pillars of Kingdoms when they ſhake and totter: If not, then, <hi>where and who is he? (Job</hi> 9. 24.) ſhew me the creature, man or Angel, that can do theſe things. The Apoſtle deſcribes unbelief to be a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from God <hi>(Heb.</hi> 3. 12.) That which carrieth us away from the fountain, carries us from the waters: that which carrieth us from the Sunne, muſt needs carry us from the light. If then unbelief carry us away from God, who is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158527:12"/> our fountain, who is our Sunne, who is all good, and who hath all good, how, or where, or by whom ſhall we be either comforted or eſtabliſhed? Is it poſſible to gain by deſerting him, who is our treaſure? upon what coaſts ſhall we trade to fraught our veſſels, when we have looſed and ſet ſayl from Heaven? As that Diſciple ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 68. when he queſtioned them, <hi>Will ye alſo go away?</hi> Go away, ſaith <hi>Peter; Lord, to whom ſhall we go? Thou haſt the words of eternall life:</hi> Where ſhall we mend our ſelves? where ſhall we have life, if we go from thee, who haſt the words of eternall life? So may we ſay, to whom ſhall we go, when a dying diſtreſſed Kingdom lies upon our hands? where ſhall we get help, or ſtrength, or deliverance, if we depart from God, the living God, the God who gives and preſerves the life both of perſons and nations?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The ſtability of a people is founded upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but unbelief attempts to ſhake the promiſes, and more, to make them of none effect. Though we have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, laden and enricht with bleſſings, yet we can do nothing with them, nor make any earnings out of them, except we ſet faith to work upon them: Nothing can fetch out the ſweetneſſe of a promiſe, but faith; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ſuck thoſe breſts, or draw water out of thoſe wels of ſalvation, but faith; faith makes a living out of a word of promiſe; but unbelief will let us die and ſtarve in the midſt and throng of all the promiſes; yea, unbelief (as to us) deſtroyeth the promiſes, and cuts the ſinews of them, ſo that they cannot ſtirre hand or foot to help us. Yet further, unbelief (as much as in it lies) turnes all the promiſes into fallacies, and the truth of God into a lie: Faith feeds upon the goodneſſe of the promiſes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:158527:12"/> devours the truth of them: Surely they ſhall never receive the good of a promiſe, who deny and deſtroy the truth of a promiſe.</p>
            <p>A fourth reaſon is this; Unbelief deſtroys all former mercies, therefore certainly unbelief will hinder future mercies: by unbelief God loſes all the favours he hath beſtowed upon us; when we beleeve not what is to be done, we unbeleeve all that God hath done. He that having been pardoned his ſinne, doth not beleeve that God will pardon him ſtill, unbeleeves that he was ever pardoned. It is ſo in the caſe of temporals: And can we think he will beſtow new favours, where he hath loſt thoſe he hath beſtowed? God will never truſt that, which diſtruſts him. The ſeven lean kine of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> eat up the fat kine; though we have had ſeven fat kine, and full ears of corn; though God hath given us ſeven full mercies, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven great deliverances, yet unbelief will ſwallow them all at a bit (as it were) and yet be as lean and empty as before: We ſee it clearly in that paſſage of the people of <hi>Iſrael, Exod.</hi> 14. 11. God had wrought a great deliverance for them, he had brought them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with a ſtrong hand, and they had ſeen the wonders of God ten times there; but as ſoon as ever they came to the red ſea, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief ſeized upon them: Oh, they ſhould never overcome that difficulty, never get paſt that danger: What doth this their unbelief? even what I have ſaid, it devoured all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer mercies: Nay, it not only took away former mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but turned them into afflictions and croſſes, ſo we may enterpret their complaint, <hi>Becauſe there were no graves in Egypt, hast thou taken us away to die in the wilderneſſe? wherefore haſt thou dealt thus with us, to carry us forth out of Egypt? for it had been better for us to ſerve the Egyptians,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:158527:13"/> 
               <hi>then that we ſhould die in the wilderneſſe.</hi> See how angry they were at former mercies, how they preferre bondage before deliverance: <hi>Wherefore haſt thou dealt thus with us, to carry us out of Egypt?</hi> Can we judge a people who are angry with former mercies, fit to receive new mercies? Such is the language of unbelief at this day: How many in their diſtreſſes, when they are brought as it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the red ſea, wiſh that this Reformation had never been begunne; it had been better for them to have ſerved their old task-maſters, both in ſpirituals and in temporals, then to endure ſuch hardſhip, then to run ſuch hazzards, and be at ſuch coſt, to free themſelves? they look upon all the wonders which God hath wrought, as matters of their ſorrow: We ſee what we have brought our ſelves to, O that we had ſuffered any thing, rather then what we ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Unbelief robs God of his honour: and that which takes glory from God, muſt needs hinder mercy from man: we can never enrich our ſelves by robbing God; <hi>unbelief is a God-robbing ſinne;</hi> and it robbes God of that which is moſt precious to him: unbelief is a bold ſinne, it goes into Gods Cabinet, and takes away his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt jewell, it takes away that which he ſaith he will not give away, <hi>his glory.</hi> The glory of God, is nothing elſe but <note place="margin">Iſa. 42. 8.</note> that reputation which he hath in the world, (I ſpeak not of his eſſentiall glory, which he hath from all eternity, and ſhall have, whether men beleeve or no; but I ſpeak of his extrinſecall, manifeſtative and declarative glory) this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief obſcureth and caſteth a vail upon, yea ſteals quite away. You know a mans glory is gone when his credit is gone; if a man be in ſuch a condition, that no man will beleeve him, or take his word, or give him credit, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158527:13"/> man hath loſt all his honour and reputation in the world: Now unbelief makes God of no credit in the world; let him ſpeak what he will, let him give his word, his hand, his covenant, his ſeal, his oath, he hath no credit among unbeleevers. It is ſaid of the old Saints <hi>(Heb.</hi> 11. 2.) <hi>that by faith they obtained a good report:</hi> There is no grace brings ſo much honour to man as faith doth; and I do aſſure you, there is no grace brings God ſo much honour as faith doth; by faith God himſelf obtains a good report among the Saints: His Name is great among thoſe who are of great faith: Gods Name is up, when our hearts are up in beleeving; and his Name is down, when our hearts are down in unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. He that receiveth the teſtimony of God, ſets to his <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 33.</note> ſeal that God is true; but he that will not receive the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of God, he (as much as he can) hath ſet to his ſeal that God is falſe. The Apoſtle quaeries, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>What if ſome did not beleeve? ſhall their unbelief make the faith of God without effect?</hi> His denying queſtion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, that this was the attempt of unbelief, even to make the faith of God, that is, the faithfullneſſe of God of none effect: It is as if he ſhould ſay, This is it which theſe by their unbelief would do, or to do which, there is a tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in unbelief; God doth and will right himſelf in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſhew himſelf faithfull, though all the world ſhould prove liars and unbeleevers: But no thanks to unbelief; that would put the higheſt diſhonour upon God, even that of falſehood to his own word, and unfaithfullneſſe to his people. Conſider this, can we thrive by endamaging God? or is it probable God will encreaſe our comforts, while we are decocting and waſting his honour?</p>
            <p>From all theſe conſiderations, the point is clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:158527:14"/> that unbelief is the ſtop of publike bleſſings, and therefore I conclude for the truth of it, That <hi>Without beleeving there can be no eſtabliſhing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence learn, firſt, how excellent and uſefull a grace faith is: Some think little of employing faith in any bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe beyond the line of the juſtification of a ſinner: But (as the Saints of old) ſo we may make other improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it. For as <hi>by faith the walls of Jericho</hi> were ſhaken and fell down <hi>(Heb.</hi> 11. 30.) ſo <hi>by faith the walls of Jeruſalem</hi> may be ſetled and raiſed up. As <hi>by faith</hi> thoſe ancient Worthies <hi>ſubdued Kingdoms:</hi> ſo <hi>by faith,</hi> at this day, we may <hi>eſtabliſh Kingdoms.</hi> We muſt not only go to prayer by faith, but to counſell by faith, and to warre by faith; by this grace we may <hi>wax valiant in fight, and turn to flight the Armies of the aliens,</hi> ver. 34. When <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphats</hi> Armies went forth to battell, his military Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had but this flower of holy rhetorique in it, <hi>Beleeve in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall you be eſtabliſhed; beleeve his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſo ſhall you proſper,</hi> 2 Chron. 20. 20. The proſperity of our worldly affairs, as well as of our heavenly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon, and flowes from the actings of our faith.</p>
            <p>In the next place, Give me leave (Honourable and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) to be an informer this day againſt the Kingdoms greateſt enemy, and the hinderer of our National eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. It was the cuſtome of the <hi>Iews</hi> (as ſome of the Learned have obſerved from the ſtory of <hi>Naboth</hi> (1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 10.) upon the day of their ſolemn faſt, to accuſe and charge notorious offenders. How many things and perſons have been, and ſtill are ſuſpected, yea charged with (that notorious offence) the ſhaking of this nation, while that which is moſt guilty, is not thought on at all by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and not enough thought on by any: I mean, and I'le
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158527:14"/> name it, <hi>unbelief.</hi> And I mean not only unbelief abroad and at large, but your own, in whoſe ears I chiefely ſpeak this day, and into whoſe hands, that great and noble work of eſtabliſhing this ſhaken, and of uniting this divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Kingdom is committed. Though it be uncomely for me to charge you, yet it is the duty of this day, for you to enquire of your own hearts, whether your own unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief hath not impeded that long prayed for, and long wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for effect and iſſue of your counſels, the eſtabliſhment of this Nation.</p>
            <p>This Nation hath been long in counſell, and yet it is not eſtabliſhed; long in action, and yet it is not eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: We have prayed long, faſted long, and yet we are not eſtabliſhed. I have the text and my point to warrant, <hi>if I accuſe and arraign unbelief as the cauſe of all this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, what hath unbelief done, or who hath ſeen it do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this evil? Unbelief is an inviſible enemy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a more dangerous enemy. But though it be inviſible in its nature, yet it is not only viſible, but palpable in its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: as holy faith alſo is. Hence, as faith is called <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall faith,</hi> and prayer <hi>effectuall prayer,</hi> becauſe theſe break forth and operate in glorious effects: ſo unbelief may be called effectuall unbelief, becauſe it breaks forth and operates in lamentable effects. And whatſoever is, or can be lookt upon as a cauſe of our continued troubles and ſhakings, is without any ſtrain or ſlander reducible to unbelief, as the cauſe of thoſe cauſes, and therefore the cauſe of thoſe effects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Some ſay, we are not eſtabliſhed, becauſe we are ſo divided. And are not our diviſions the fruit of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief? <hi>Hearts not joyned in faith to God, cannot joyn, or not firmely joyn to one another in love.</hi> They that go off from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:158527:15"/> God (and every act of unbelief in us, is a ſtep from him) ſeldome keep cloſe to one another, <hi>Faith is the cement and ſoder of affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If it be ſaid, we are not eſtabliſhed, becauſe ſtill ſo unreformed, ſinne abounds ſtill, and therefore trouble abounds ſtill, I grant it. But whence is it that ſinne abounds? I muſt ſet that alſo upon the head of unbelief. It is unbelief which protects ſinne, and keeps it alive, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſentence of death hath gone out ſo often againſt it: Though it hath ſo often (in theſe ſin-morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying duties of prayer and faſting) been carried out to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. Sinne laughs at all our daies of ſorrow and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, at our faſts and prayers, while unbelief backs and ſtands to it. For as <hi>faith is a ſhield to the new-man, which quenches all the fiery darts of the Devil: ſo unbelief is a ſhield to the old-man, which quenches all the holy darts of the Spirit.</hi> The word cannot wound a ſinner, while he is armed with unbelief. Sinne will ſave its skinne, much more its heart, till faith ſets it naked to the ſtroaks and ſmitings of the word.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If it be ſaid, Surely we are not eſtabliſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are grown ſo careleſſe, ſo cold and formall in thoſe <hi>Kingdom-establiſhing duties, faſting and prayer.</hi> Many neglect to keep them, as counting ſuch daies loſt out of the calendar of their lives: But moſt are negligent in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and have turned the whole buſineſſe into a meer bodily exerciſe, or the <hi>hanging down of their heads for a day:</hi> This neglect to keep faſts, and negligent keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, is ſo groſſe and notorious, that it makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts to bleed while they think of it. Hence ſome have thought it moſt ſafe, to move for the ſuperſedeating of theſe duties, fearing that ſuch ſetled faſts will but more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:158527:15"/> unſettle the Kingdom, and rather provoke the Lord, then pacifie him towards us. Reaſons may be given for the laying down of theſe Monethly, and the keeping only of occaſionall faſts: though in one ſenſe our monethly faſts are occaſionall, the great occaſion why they began, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to this day. But how ſad is it, to conſider that this ſhould be given as a reaſon, That we have laid down theſe faſts, becauſe we are weary keeping them, or are grown formall in keeping of them. To break off from ſuch a duty, upon theſe terms, is a lamentation, and will be one: What? have we faſted away the tenderneſſe of our hearts, and our ſenſibleneſſe of Gods hand? have we prayed away our zeal for God, and our love to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him? this is dreadfull.</p>
            <p>But how dreadfull ſoever it is; this (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) if it be ſo, muſt be charged upon unbelief. Why do any neglect faſts? it is, becauſe they do not beleeve it will quit coſt to obſerve them; they beleeve more gain is to be got by working in their callings, and more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort will come in by letting themſelves out in pleaſures: &amp; therefore they will not forbear their labours, or abridge themſelves for a day of their pleaſures. No man will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict his body (as in ſuch daies he muſt) much leſſe his ſoul (as in ſuch daies he ought) unleſſe faith ſhew him a benefit, which will bear his charge, and comforts, which will ſwallow up his ſorrows, in doing them.</p>
            <p>And whence is it, that many who appear outwardly in theſe duties, are ſo formall, rather perſonating the faſter and petitioner, then being faſters and petitioners? is it not from unbelief? They who have ſlight thoughts of a duty, muſt needs act it ſlightly.</p>
            <p>And whence is it, that prayer and faſting are at any time
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:158527:16"/> ſucceſſeleſſe and ineffectuall? is not this from unbelief? Praying without beleeving, is a taking of Gods Name in vain, and (in regard of any fruit) a vain help for man. Prayer without faith, is nothing but a noiſe of words, <hi>meer babling:</hi> it is but ſpeaking, not praying. In the ſixth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chriſt reproves thoſe, who thought to be heard for their <hi>much ſpeaking.</hi> We ſhall ſurely be heard if we <hi>pray</hi> but a little, but we ſhall never be heard how much ſoever we <hi>ſpeak.</hi> And if faith be mixt in the duty, how long ſoever we continue ſpeaking, how many words, yea repetitions ſoever we uſe in it, Chriſt will not call it <hi>much ſpeaking,</hi> but <hi>much praying:</hi> Though he reproved <hi>much ſpeaking,</hi> yet he neither did, nor ever will reprove <hi>much praying:</hi> Now unbelief makes that which is commonly called praying, how much ſoever it is, to be but <hi>much ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> And for that (becauſe Chriſt is not in it) neither man nor nation ſhall be heard. The eſtabliſhing of an unſetled Kingdom, calls (as for the higheſt and pureſt motions of reaſon in counſelling, ſo) for the holieſt and moſt ſpirituall motions of faith in praying: But as unbelief darkens the light of reaſon, that it cannot ſee, or holds it in unrighteouſneſſe; ſo it clips the wings of prayer, that it cannot aſcend, or returns it anſwerleſſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Should it be ſaid, <hi>Instruments have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, they have not acted up to the highest, either of their abilities, or of their duties, and therefore ſurely we are not eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed:</hi> Then, I muſt <hi>return</hi> unbelief as guilty of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfullneſſe. Want of faith is the cauſe of all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfullneſſe that ever was in the world; the very root of apoſtaſie both from God and man. Faith keeps the heart ſteady, and will ſee us die, rather then offer a thought of withdrawing from a known duty: <hi>Faith blaſts all tempting</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:158527:16"/> 
               <hi>objects; yea, it out-bids all tempers,</hi> ſhewing greater good in doing our duty, then the world can offer us for omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or falling off from it; ſhewing us greater evil in neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting our duty, then the world can threaten us with for doing or comming up to it. When <hi>Paul</hi> began to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> (1 Ep. 3. 5, 6, 7.) <hi>Leſt by ſome means the tempter had tempted them,</hi> he preſently ſent a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to them, <hi>to know how their faith did;</hi> and as ſoon as the meſſenger returned, bringing <hi>good tiding of their faith;</hi> namely, that their faith was in heart, and in good plight, <hi>Paul was comforted;</hi> he knew, as long as their faith ſtood, they would ſtand againſt all temptations; he might turn them looſe into the world, they would take no hurt. A beleever is the greateſt conquerer. <hi>This is the victory that overcommeth the world, even our faith</hi> (1 Joh. 5. 4.) and that which betrayes us into the hand of every temptation, is unbelief: It makes men act baſely, and render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves priſoners to every promiſe of preferment, or hope of profit, to every whiſpering threat of danger, and fear of loſſe. Where unbelief reigns, it either divides the man, or amazes him: either it makes him an <hi>hypocrite</hi> with two hearts, or a <hi>coward</hi> without a heart: <hi>And between thoſe who have two hearts, and thoſe who have no hearts, the beſt work in the world may ſoon miſcarry.</hi> Unbelief nurſes ignoble emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, undue ambitions, baſe covetouſneſſe; it moves to ſelf-ſeeking, caries to ſelf-ends, makes the ſpirit poor and private; it bids us ſhift and comply with all humours, and adviſes to follow, not the reaſon, goodneſſe, truth or juſtice of an undertaking, but the ſucceſſes or advantages of it.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Some charge our unſettlement upon <hi>unreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſſe, fearfullneſſe and want of courage,</hi> in carrying on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:158527:17"/> the work. If ſo, <hi>Theſe alſo</hi> (I ſee by their complexion) are <hi>the children of unbelief:</hi> for that is it, which cauſeth a man to hang like a meteor in the ayr, between Heaven and earth, not knowing which way to move. They who have little faith, have much fear, and they who have no faith are in a readineſſe to be all fear, to be ſlain by fear: ſo were they of whom the Prophet <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſpeaks (chap. 22. 1.) <hi>They are ſlain, and not by the ſword:</hi> Fear ſaves the enemy a labour; courage in battell is uſually flatted by unbelief; and though ſome may ſhew valour who have no faith, yet faith is the trueſt ſpring and ſupport of valour; <hi>By faith they waxed valiant in fight, Heb.</hi> 11. Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in counſelling and reforming fades alſo and dies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by unbelief: <hi>Vnbelief makes a man afraid of diſpleaſing any one, but God:</hi> It ſpeakes as the meſſenger to <hi>Micaiah,</hi> (1 King. 22. 13.) <hi>Let thy word be like one of them, and ſpeak that which is good.</hi> Many have given counſell before, ſuiting both the humour and deſign of the King; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid that meſſenger, do thou vote with them too, let there be no diſſent among the Prophets, <hi>ſpeak that which is good;</hi> that which is pleaſingly good, (he meant) no matter whether it be juſtly or truly good; elſe it may go ill with thee, thou mayeſt be caſt in priſon, and fed with the <hi>bread of affliction, and the water of affliction.</hi> With ſuch words as theſe, will unbelief (if it be admitted to ſpeak its minde) prepare the heart for counſell every morning: It tells ſuch fearfull ſtories, or lying prophecies rather, as will not let a man ſpeak or act beyond his own intereſts.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> made that bold reformation, removing the high places, breaking the Images, cutting down the groves, and breaking in pieces the brazen ſerpent that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> made (and was now made an Idol) calling it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158527:17"/> 
               <hi>Nehuſhtan:</hi> to the record of thoſe noble acts, the Holy Ghoſt affixes the character of the agent, <hi>He trusted in the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18. 4, 5. What difficulty or danger <hi>will not truſt in God, carry man thorow, in Gods way:</hi> And ſutely it carried <hi>Hezekiah</hi> thorow very great ones in that his zealous reformation. What viſions of fear and danger might unbelief have repreſented to <hi>Hezekiah?</hi> What! remove the higheſt places? it may remove you from your high place: will you cut down the groves? that act may cut down your life: will you break the Images, eſpecially that <hi>famous one, the Brazen ſerpent?</hi> take heed it be not the breaking of your Kingdome: Do you not know how your people are engaged to theſe courſes? I grant they are ſuperſtitious, but this nation will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily part with them, if you will be ſo ſtrict in reforming, you may embroil all: Conſider what the Kingdom will bear, enquire how the City will take this, and how the countrey; it is wiſedom to look to your own peace, and to follow ſafe counſels, as well as right or holy counſels. How did the faith of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> triumph over theſe diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging baſe ſuggeſtions? And if ever any have been or ſhall be led into captivity by their power, reſolve it, that man was firſt captivated by unbelief.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Some charge our non-eſtabliſhment, upon our <hi>carnall confidence, our trusting in an arme of fleſh;</hi> They will tell us, we have made an <hi>Idol of the Parliament,</hi> an <hi>Idol of our Armies,</hi> we have leaned ſo much upon our ſtaves, that we have broken ſome of them, crackt others, and endangered the reſt.</p>
            <p>If this be a true charge, I muſt lay it, as all the former, upon the back of unbelief. They who beleeve God too little, do alwaies beleeve man too much; that which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:158527:18"/> makes God but as a man, will quickly make man as a God whereas faith, while it cauſes us to be ſo diligent in the uſe of means, as if God would do nothing for us, cauſeth us ſo to withdraw our truſt from the means, as if God were to do all for us; faith ſhews us as much need of God in our fullneſſe, as in our wants. <hi>It is a hard thing to depend upon God, in the weakneſſe and want of means, but it is harder to depend upon him in the fullneſſe and ſtrength of means.</hi> This is the nobleſt act of faith: And though (we know) in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſenſe will ſwallow up faith, yet on earth faith ought to ſwallow up our ſenſe; When we ſee, and hear, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy moſt of the creature, we ſhould be as if we heard, and ſaw, and enjoyed nothing of the creature, but lived upon God alone. Obſerve this inſtanced in two great Kings: <hi>Aſa had an Army of men that bare targets and ſpears, out of Iudah three hundred thouſand, and out of Benjamin that bare ſhields and drew bowes, two hundred and fourſcore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. 8. A gallant Army: Yet when <hi>Zerah</hi> the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> came againſt him with a more numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>Aſa cried unto the Lord his God, and ſaid, Lord, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with thee to help with many, or with them that have no power,</hi> ver. 11. But are ſix hundred thouſand men <hi>no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Aſa's</hi> faith ſaw no power in this compleat Army, that he might ſee all power in God, and engage him in the battell; <hi>We reſt on thee, let not man prevail againſt thee.</hi> He makes nothing of his Army, in caſe of victory, while he made nothing of it in caſe of an overthrow: <hi>Let not man prevail against thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> is yet more full, who had an Army of eleven hundred and threeſcore thouſand fighting men (beſides his Gariſons) for the field, as appears upon his muſter-roll, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 14, 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet when the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:158527:18"/> 
               <hi>Moabites</hi> and the <hi>Ammonites</hi> made warre upon him, he prays thus <hi>(chap</hi> 20. 12.) <hi>O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might againſt this great company that commeth againſt us, neither know we what to do, but our eyes are upon thee.</hi> What, had he no might? knew he not what to do, when he had 1160000 men in the field? No, not he: He had no eye to ſee theſe or any thing, but God; and therefore ſaith, <hi>Our eyes are</hi> (not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Armies, but) <hi>upon thee.</hi> In this faith of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures nothingneſſe, and the all-ſufficiencie of God, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> as <hi>Aſa</hi> had done before over <hi>Zerah the Ethiopian.</hi> We then receive moſt by humane helps, when we expect leaſt; unbelief either takes our hearts off from God, or (which is as dangerous) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides them upon the creature; for when we lean upon two, of which one is infirm, we ſhall not ſtand by that which is ſtrong, but fall by that which is weak: faith bids us uſe means, and unbelief bids us truſt it: And though faith will truſt ſome means, in regard of their faithfullneſſe, yet it will truſt none, in regard of effectualneſſe. As God calls for all our obedience, ſo for all our confidence; confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in man is ever accompanied with jealouſies upon God; ſuch confidences God rejects, and therefore we have not, we cannot proſper in them.</p>
            <p>Should this inquiſition be enlarg'd, and the lot caſt to finde out every accurſed thing, which hath obſtructed the influences of Heaven, from making this Land a quiet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, I might with like eaſe and cleerneſſe reſolve them all into unbelief; and therefore I leave unbelief un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the guilt of this <hi>grand charge, The Kingdoms enemy, the helliſh vapour which continues this our long Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and State-quake;</hi> or in the word of the text, <hi>The ſtop of our eſtabliſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:158527:19"/>
            <p> Let me then a while call in the help of faith, as the nobleſt expedient for the cure of all our evils? It is ſaid <hi>(Joh.</hi> 7. 37.) that, <hi>In the laſt day of the feaſt, Jeſus ſtood and cried, ſaying; He that beleeveth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water:</hi> Will it not be ſeaſonable, in this great day of your <hi>Faſt</hi> and ſolemn humiliation, to lift up a voice for faith, and cry out, ſaying, <hi>If ye beleeve, ſurely ye ſhall be establiſhed?</hi> Set faith awork, in every work, let it be an ingredient in all your counſels, in all your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Ye act but as men, not as the people of God, as a <hi>Roman,</hi> not as a Chriſtian Senate, without faith. As by faith <hi>Abel</hi> offered God a better ſacrifice then <hi>Cain</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo by faith, one offers the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>state,</hi> better advice then his neighbour. When you prepare armes and Armies, arme your ſelves with <hi>this ſhield.</hi> Faith is the beſt weapon, <hi>It will quench the fiery darts of men, as well as the fiery darts of the Devil;</hi> if your Armies were weak, faith would recruit and ſtrengthen them; now they are ſtrong, faith will continue and encreaſe them: when your affairs are at a ſtand, faith will put them in motion, faith is a friend at a dead lift. If there be but a little meal in your barrell, and a little oyl in your cruze, faith will lead you into the ſtore-houſes of Heaven, and ſhew you all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and riches which are laid up there. As <hi>Hezekiah</hi> led the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Babylon</hi> from chamber to chamber, and ſhewed them all the riches and proviſions of his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all houſe, both for peace and warre; ſo will faith (but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better principles) take you by the hand, and lead you from one attribute of God to another, and ſhew you all fullneſſe of all things, there unſearchable riches of mercy, here unchangeable faithfullneſſe, there infinite ſtrength, and here pureſt exacteſt wiſedom to improve and manage
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:158527:19"/> it: We can never be at a loſſe while we can beleeve, for that will finde out helpe for us, when ſenſe can ſee none, when reaſon and policie can project none.</p>
            <p>If Information be deſired, how or when we act by faith towards publike eſtabliſhment, take it thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Faith acts in the ſtrength, upon the truth and goodneſſe of a promiſe. Promiſes are the aire and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in which faith breathes and lives. Faith languiſhes, unleſſe fed and dieted by divine engagements; it reliſhes no fare, but of Gods own providing; it muſt have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in the word, or a promiſe in the works of God to reſt upon. The works of God have a promiſe in them, as well as the word of God, and are therefore the <hi>objects of faith,</hi> not only as faith notes the beleeving of what is done, but alſo as it notes the beleeving of what is to be done; In which ſenſe we are to underſtand that reproof of the Jews, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 32. <hi>They beleeved not his wondrous works.</hi> They did beleeve, the hiſtory of his works, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſuch things as are there recorded, were done; They could not but beleeve that God had wrought wonders for them in <hi>Egypt,</hi> that he had drowned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in, and brought them ſafe thorow, the red ſea: they ſaw theſe things, their ſenſes were witneſſes; but yet they did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the <hi>prophecie or promiſe,</hi> which was vertually in thoſe works, namely that God would do more wonders for them, till he had finiſht and accompliſht their deliverance: That hiſtory of their bringing thorow the red ſea, had this prophecie in it, that they ſhould be brought ſafe to <hi>Canaan;</hi> but they did not beleeve the voice of this prophecie: When God gave them water out of the rock, this work promiſed, that he would give them meat out of the clouds, if they needed it; but this they beleeved not:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:158527:20"/> Hence the ſame Pſalme reports their unbelief, under this notion, <hi>ver.</hi> 19, 20. <hi>They ſpake againſt God, they ſaid, Can God furniſh a table in the wilderneſse? Behold, he ſmote the rock, that the waters guſhed out, and the ſtreams over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed; Can he give bread alſo? Can he provide fleſh alſo for his people? When the Lord heard this</hi> (language of unbelief) <hi>he was wroth.</hi> Then faith moves in the higheſt region of holineſſe, when it ſees all to be done, in what is done; when it reads meat promiſed in waters given; and conquers a <hi>Goliah</hi> in the conqueſt of a Lion: when a <hi>ſlain Leviathan is its food in the wilderneſſe.</hi> And thus the Lord directs the faith of his ancient people <hi>(Deut.</hi> 7. 17.) to outwreſtle the greateſt dangers, <hi>If thou ſhalt ſay in thine heart, theſe Nations are moe then I, how can I diſpoſseſſe them? thou ſhalt not be afraid of them, but ſhalt well remember what the Lord thy God did unto Pharaoh, and unto all Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. Hence the reaſon why the people of Iſrael provoked God at the red ſea by their fears and murmurings, is thus given <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 106. 7.) <hi>They remembred not the multitude of thy mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then (at any time) you think your ſelves ſcanted in promiſes, ſend back your thoughts to thoſe many expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences, both of elder and later dates: The invincible Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy in 88. overcome; the ſecret Powder-plot diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and blown up; your yeſterday protections, deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſucceſſes, victories, ſhould all be ſerved up to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of your hearts, for faith to feed upon, and nouriſh it ſelf up into a holy confidence, <hi>That he who hath delivered you from ſo great a death, and doth deliver, will yet deliver you, that thanks may be given by us all in this behalf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As faith <hi>acts upon the truth and goodneſſe of a promiſe,</hi> ſo alwaies <hi>by the juſtice and holineſſe of a rule.</hi> No
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:158527:20"/> man can act that by faith, which is either unlawfull to be done, or is done unlawfully. Faith acts in the eye of God, and therefore muſt act holily. Faith tells us that God hath no need of our ſins, to promote his cauſe, and that we muſt not <hi>lye for God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, He that acts by faith, will look that his end be as good as his rule. As faith will not do evil that good may come of it, ſo neither will it do good that evil may come of it, or that ſuch a private perſonall good may come of it, as is over-balanc'd with publike generall evils. <hi>Faith never drives a trade <hi>(knowingly)</hi> for it ſelf, with wrong to the common ſtock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Faith carries with it cheerfullneſſe oppoſite to worldly ſorrow, courage oppoſite to worldly fear, reſolvedneſſe oppoſite to baſe neutralitry, zeal oppoſite to lazie lukewarmeneſſe, boldneſſe oppoſite to ſinfull modeſty, and a ſober confidence of ſucceſſe, or an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that our labour ſhall not be in vain, oppoſite to all heart-ſinking doubts, and deſpondencies of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Thus he doth, who acts by faith, and all this, faith will do; yet, not every faith; True faith will do the former three, but the fourth is a task for ſtrong faith. It was the Apoſtles caution, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Him that is weak in the faith receive, but not to doubtfull diſputations. The works of God put us as hard queſtions as his word.</hi> The diſputes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence are often very hard diſputes: A weak faith may ſoon be overmatch by them. But where faith is ſtrong and vigorous, it will unty all thoſe knots, reſolve all thoſe doubts, run thorow all that work, with eaſe. That muſt needs keep our ſouls ſteady, and make us unwearied in the work of the Lord, which fetches in conſtant ſupplies, and feeds our lamp with oil as faſt as it ſpends, which wipes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:158527:21"/> off our ſweat, and cauſeth us to act in his ſtrength, who can do all things.</p>
            <p>But were it not better to fear alwaies, then to be ſo high ſlown in faith? were it not better to prepare for the worſt times, then to be confident of good, or better?</p>
            <p>I do not counſell any to ſlacken their preparation for evil and worſer times, while I ſtirre up your mindes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and waite for the beſt. Sit down as oft as you pleaſe, and prepare for death, for ſword, for famine and for ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Sit down, and commune with your own hearts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your beds about theſe things: Put the caſe to your ſelves, and act the part of ſufferers under hardeſt preſſures: Think what to do if the ſword were at your breſts, and the fire in your houſes. But in the midſt of your prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for evil, take heed of caſting away the hopes of good. <hi>An evil heart of unbelief, is ſeven fold worſe then all the evils that can fall upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though (all the unkinde diſtractions and diviſions at home, with the oppoſitions abroad being conſidered) the way of faith lies very much up-hill, yea up moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and craggy rocks, yet know, <hi>There is no danger ſo great, or exigent ſo dreadfull, which can be a plea for unbelief.</hi> If any people might have been excuſed for their unbelief, the people of Iſrael might; for they had an Army behind them, the ſea before them, and the mountains on either ſide, ſo that the enemy ſaid, <hi>I will purſue, I will overtake, I will divide the ſpoile, my lust ſhall be ſatisfied upon them, I will draw my ſword, mine hand ſhall deſtroy them</hi> (Exod. 15. 9.) yet their unbelief is taxed as a provocation. <hi>Never ſpeak of the greatneſſe of danger to leſsen faith:</hi> for dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are the element of faith; among them faith lives moſt, becauſe among them faith findes moſt promiſes.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:158527:21"/> When we have leaſt of the world about us, we have moſt of the word about us; and when we have moſt of the world againſt us, we have more of the word for us. Faith hath beſt food in famine, the fulleſt table in a wilderneſſe. Faith (like the Horſe <hi>(Job</hi> 39. 19.) <hi>rejoyceth in its ſtrength, (for it is the ſtrength of God) and goeth out to meet the armed men. Faith mocketh at fear, and is not affrighted, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turneth back from the ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort mannage the objection further: We know God is able (be the difficulties never ſo great) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver, but we are not acquainted with his will: How then can we act faith? how can we be confident as you would have us? We, indeed, may ſay as he in the Goſpell, <hi>Lord if thou wilt, thou canſt make us clean: thou canst ſettle and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh us:</hi> But we are uncertain of his will, though we are ſure of his power.</p>
            <p>To theſe I anſwer: Firſt, That howſoever the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the will of God be uſually held forth as a plea for doubting and unbelief; yet moſt doubt and are unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving upon ſuſpition of the power of God: For when faith is up, and acts ſtrongly upon this point, <hi>that God is able,</hi> it ſeldome doubts about his will. We have a great inſtance of this, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 19. when God promiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpread ſuch a table in the wilderneſſe, that all the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites ſhould eat fleſh, <hi>not only one day, or two daies, or five daies, or ten daies, or twenty daies, but even a whole moneth: Moſes</hi> begins to argue, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>The people, amongſt whom I am, are ſix hundred thouſand foot-men, and thou haſt ſaid, I will give them fleſh that they may eat a whole moneth</hi> (As if <hi>Moſes</hi> had ſaid; Lord, I pray conſider your words, are you able to make good your promiſe?) <hi>ſhall the flocks, and the herds be ſlain for them to ſuffice them? Or ſhall the fiſh of the</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:158527:22"/> 
               <hi>ſea be gathered together for them to ſuffice them?</hi> What is the meaning of theſe queſtions? even that <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf doubted whether God could performe this, whether God had not out-promiſed his own power. That it was ſo, is ſeen clearly by the anſwer that God makes, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, Is the Lords hand waxed ſhort? Thou ſhalt ſee now whether my word ſhall come to paſſe or not.</hi> The hand of God is the power of God, and the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his hand, the ſhortning of his power. Is Gods power ſhortned? <hi>Moſes</hi> his queſtion intimated that it was: So <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 1. <hi>The Lords hand is not ſhortned that he cannot ſave:</hi> Now as in Common-wealths, good Laws ſhew ill manners (for Laws are medicines, applied by wiſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to cure the ſeverall diſtempers of a people) ſo good counſels and proofs ſhew the evil which is in the heart of man. When God askes the queſtion, <hi>Is my hand ſhortned?</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>My hand is not ſhortned,</hi> we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Jews had an apprehenſion that Gods hand was ſhortned, that his power was not ſo great as he had reported.</p>
            <p>Again, If it be not doubting of the power of God; why do we beleeve leaſt when dangers are greateſt? in little dangers we beleeve God is willing; why not in greater dangers? ſurely, becauſe then a greater power is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; ſo that the ſtick is at the power of God, though uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his will be pretended. When <hi>Abraham, that mighty giant in beleeving,</hi> had overcome this difficulty, that God was able, nothing ſtood in his way, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 19, 20. <hi>Being not weak in faith, he conſidered not his own body now dead, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet the deadneſse of Sarah's womb, he ſtaggered not at the promiſe of God through unbelief, but was ſtrong in faith, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving glory to God, and being fully perſwaded, that he who had</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:158527:22"/> 
               <hi>promiſed, was able alſo to performe.</hi> Obſerve, he doth not ſay that <hi>Abraham</hi> was fully perſwaded God was willing to performe what he had promiſed; <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted moſt, to aſſure and ſettle him that God was able to performe: And as ſoon as he gave glory to God by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving him all-ſufficient, his faith had no ſtop. So the holy Ghoſt expreſſeth the other great triall of his faith <hi>(Heb.</hi> 11. 19.) when he was called to ſacrifice his ſonne, he was in a great ſtrait; but in what was his faith moſt tried? It was about the power of God; God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him a ſonne, and in that ſonne a great bleſſing to himſelf and all Nations; Now, the text ſaith not, that he doubted not of the will of God, <hi>but he accounted that God was able to raiſe him up from the dead: from whence alſo he had received him in a figure:</hi> when he was ſetled in that, he never ſtaid at the offering up his ſonne. And if we ſearch our hearts to the bottome, we ſhall finde that our doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings reflect moſt upon the power of God, and we ſhorten his hand, though we commonly ſay, we are uncertain of his will.</p>
            <p>I anſwer ſecondly, to thoſe who ſay they doubt of the will of God, and not of his power, that though we cannot directly and poſitively affirm, God will do a thing becauſe he can do it; yet there is a mighty argument to help faith out, that God will do a thing when we are aſſured that he can: Where there wants power, faith cannot work at all. When the woman in <hi>Samaria</hi> beſpake the King (2 <hi>King.</hi> 6. 27.) <hi>Help, my Lord O King;</hi> the King anſwered her, <hi>If the Lord do not help thee, whence ſhall I help thee? out of the barne-floor, or out of the wine-preſse.</hi> As if he had ſaid, There's nothing in the barne, nothing in the wine-preſſe; and I cannot make corne or wine. What could this woman
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:158527:23"/> expect further? Where power is at an end, faith is at an end too: But ſeeing the power of God is never at an end, therefore our faith in comming to him needs not.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God hath expreſt himſelf in Scripture, as much, yea more, for his willingneſſe, then for his power to help; therefore we need not make our uncertainty of his will the reaſon of our unbelief, when we ſay, we are aſſured of his power: God hath ſaid, <hi>He is Almighty;</hi> &amp;c. but there are not onely words importing that God is willing to help his people, but promiſes and oaths that he will <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 50. 15.) <hi>Call upon me, and I will deliver thee, Eze.</hi> 33. 11. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked</hi> (that place is meant primarily of a civill death, a death in trouble) <hi>but that the wicked turn from his way and live.</hi> Yea, God hath manifeſted a willingneſſe to help a people, which his power hath not ſeconded; but he never mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his power, when his will did not concurre: that moſt paſſionate exclamation, <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, How often would I have gathered thee! &amp;c.</hi> Implies a generall willingneſſe in Chriſt to gather Jeruſalem, yet Chriſt did not act his divine power effectually for their gathering.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſay to ſuch, though we may not argue that God will do a thing becauſe he hath power; yet we may argue from the power of God, that a thing ſhall be done, if he hath already expreſſed any willingneſſe to do it, and made any offers or aſſayes towards the doing of it. The Apoſtle would have the weak brother received <hi>(Rom.</hi> 14. 1.) upon this ground, <hi>He ſhall be holden up. (verſ.</hi> 4.) He affirmes confidently, that <hi>He ſhall be holden up;</hi> what doth he ground this confidence upon? upon the will of God? No, upon his power, <hi>For God is able to make him ſtand:</hi> But how could the Apoſtle argue thus peremptorily from
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:158527:23"/> the power of God that the thing ſhould be done? He gave intimation before of the willingneſſe of God, for he had ſaid in the cloſe of the third verſe, <hi>God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him;</hi> I ſee God hath favoured this man, though he be weak, therefore becauſe I ſee he is one, on whom God hath beſtowed ſome mercy already, I will therefore ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue confidently, that mercy ſhall be perfected; he ſhall ſtand, becauſe God is able to make him ſtand, <hi>for he hath received him.</hi> We may argue thus for the publike; <hi>This Kingdom ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make it ſtand:</hi> How ſo? <hi>God hath received it:</hi> Do yee perceive no break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth of the love of God to his people in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Hath he done nothing which intimates <hi>he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this people?</hi> Surely, he hath, therefore we may ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue; <hi>God is able to make us stand; therefore we ſhall be hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en up, for God hath received us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third objection is thus raiſed: You will have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that we ſhall be eſtabliſhed, but I pray ſhew us a word for our faith: Can you give us any promiſe? <hi>Iſaiah</hi> here brought a promiſe immediatly from Heaven, he told the people from the mouth of God, that they ſhould be eſtabliſhed; can you do ſo too? Faith is a wiſe grace; Faith loves not to build upon the ſand, much leſſe to build caſtles in the ayr; Faith muſt have a ſure foundation, and nothing will ſerve faiths turne, but the word of God; It will not build upon the bare word of all the Preachers in the world; As the great Mathematician ſaid; <hi>Shew me a place where I ſhall ſet mine engine, and I will ſhake all the earth;</hi> ſo ſaith faith, Give me but a ſure word whereupon I may fix my foot, I will carry any thing; but where is that word to be found? <hi>whats the text, chapter and verſe, that England ſhall be establiſhed?</hi> or have you any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary revelation, that it ſhall?</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:158527:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:158527:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:158527:25"/>
            <p>'Tis granted, We have no ſuch revelations as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> brought to <hi>Ahaz</hi> and his people; but we have that which ſerves faiths turn ſufficiently; and ſo much as amounts to a particular promiſe. I may ſay, <hi>There is as much ground in Scripture for faith to build on, for the preſent temporall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of this diſtreſſed Kingdom, as any man at firſt hath, or had in Scripture to beleeve his eternall ſalvation.</hi> I clear it thus; Suppoſe we comming to a man lying in the ſtate of nature, and under trouble of conſcience for his ſinne, ſhould offer him Chriſt, and pardon, and he ſhould ſay, Shew a promiſe which belongs to me: What promiſe could we tender him? could we bring one, with his name literally in it? doth any promiſe ſpeak explicitely, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, or John, do thou beleeve, and thou ſhalt be ſaved?</hi> There is no ſuch word for the ſalvation of any man. There are promiſes of three ſorts in Scripture. Firſt, Promiſes of <hi>free grace,</hi> that <hi>God will juſtifie the ungodly, and pardon ſinne, for his own Names ſake.</hi> Secondly, Promiſes <hi>of grace, that God will give faith, repentance, love, and a new heart,</hi> &amp;c. Thirdly, Promiſes <hi>unto grace,</hi> that <hi>if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and repent, we ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Promiſes of theſe three ſorts, are all we have to build our faith upon for eternall ſalvation; and theſe we, or any other Nation that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame condition, hath to build aſſurance upon for temporall ſalvation. There are promiſes <hi>of free grace</hi> to Nations, that God will deliver and ſave them for his own Names ſake: ſuch a promiſe we have, though the Name of <hi>England</hi> be not expreſſed in it. Again, there are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of grace to Nations, <hi>that God will poure out a ſpirit of repentance and humiliation upon them, and cauſe them to return.</hi> Laſtly, we have promiſes unto grace, that if a people call upon God, repent and turn from their evil waies, they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:158527:25"/> ſhall be delivered, <hi>If my people which are called by my Name, do humble themſelves, and ſeek my face, and pray, and turn unto me, I will hear in Heaven and deliver,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 7. 14. Theſe promiſes were made not only <hi>to the people of Iſrael,</hi> but to all people who are <hi>the Iſrael of God.</hi> Say not then, this ſtops your faith, ye cannot beleeve eſtabliſhment, becauſe ye want a promiſe of eſtabliſhment; theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are ours, as well as this was <hi>Jeruſalems.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe objections and ſtumbling-blocks being thus (I hope) anſwered and removed out of the way of faith: let your faith gird up her loynes, and rejoyce like a giant to run her race.</p>
            <p>Act faith for the Kingdom, as you would for your own ſouls. Is it not a duty, to beleeve when you pray and ſeek God about temporals (in their degree and kinde) as well as when about ſpirituals and eternals in theirs? Hath not God given his people ſometimes as clear evidences, as ſtrong aſſurances that their prayers have been heard about temporals, as about eternals? What if we ſhould not be under the influences of thoſe promiſes which are made <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grace,</hi> to a repenting, reforming people: yet faith hath footing enough in thoſe which are made <hi>of grace,</hi> to give give repentance and reformation to a people, and in thoſe of <hi>free-grace, that God will ſave for his Name ſake,</hi> though a people are generally impenitent and unreformed. <hi>A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of prevailing, is a ſufficient ground both for praying and beleeving.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Joel (chap.</hi> 2. 14) perſwades that afflicted people to faſt and pray (in that he perſwaded them to beleeve) upon this offer only, <hi>Who knoweth if he will return and repent? Nineve</hi> is carried up to beleeve by the ſame argument <hi>(Jon.</hi> 3. 9.) <hi>Who can tell, if God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn?</hi> A peradventure from God, is better then an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:158527:26"/> promiſe from any creature. So long as God hath not ſaid, <hi>hee will not,</hi> though hee hath not ſaid <hi>hee will,</hi> let us venture; God hath not yet forbidden prayer, but rather beſpoken it in the hearts of his people: God hath not yet declared by any work of providence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>England,</hi> as he did againſt <hi>Judah</hi> by his word <hi>(Jer.</hi> 15. 1, 2.) <hi>Though Moſes, and Samuel ſtood before me, yet my minde could not be towards this people; cast them out of my ſight, and let them go forth, ſuch as for death to death,</hi> &amp;c. No, he hath rather declared his willingneſſe, if not his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedneſſe to deliver, to ſave, to ſettle, to eſtabliſh us: His heart ſeems to work toward us, let our faith work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him; yea, let our faith have a perfect work, and then (I doubt not) but God will perfect all our works, <hi>If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, ſurely we ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, If a ſhaking Kingdom be eſtabliſhed by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, then, <hi>how precious are beleevers!</hi> Are they not the <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and pillars of a ſtate? Job</hi> puts the queſtion concerning wiſedom <hi>(chap.</hi> 28. 12.) <hi>Where ſhall wiſedom be found? and where is the place of underſtanding? The depth ſaith, It is not in me, and the ſea ſaith, It is not with me,</hi> ver. 14. Should I put ſuch a quaerie about the point in hand, <hi>Where ſhall the ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Nation be found? and what is the place of its ſtrength?</hi> Your <hi>ſea</hi> would ſay, It is not in me, and your <hi>ſhips</hi> would ſay, It is not in us; your <hi>Gariſons</hi> in fortified Cities, and your <hi>Armies</hi> in the open field, your <hi>correſpondencies</hi> abroad, and your <hi>counſels</hi> at home, would, or muſt all bring in their <hi>diſclaimers,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Strength is not in us, in us establiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not to be found.</hi> Where is it then? the text anſwers, <hi>Faith is our ſtrength, eſtabliſhing is by beleeving: Beleevers are establiſhers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if they be ſo uſefull, let them be as acceptable: It
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:158527:26"/> is but equall, that they who do the publike ſo much good, ſhould receive good from the publike: I am ſure it is not ſafe to let them be diſcouraged, by whom our ſafety is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, much leſſe is it ſafe to let them fall, by whom (in their capacity) Kingdoms ſtand, or to caſt them down, who (by the rule of Divine politicks) are <hi>ſtate-up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Stephen</hi> is deſcribed <hi>(Act.</hi> 6. 8.) A man <hi>full of faith and of power</hi> (where ſaith is, power is not farre off) yet this man was ſtoned <hi>(chap.</hi> 7. 59.) How ſad a ſpectacle was it to ſee a man ſtoned to death, whoſe life was (like a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or corner-ſtone) eſtabliſhment to the whole building.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But many pretend faith, who have no conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am no advocate for ſuch, for their faith is vain, and they are yet in their ſins. And yet (I conceive) it is better for a <hi>ſuppoſed faiths</hi> ſake to ſpare ſome, who (in the iſſue) will be found to have no conſcience, then for conſcience ſake to afflict any, who (in the iſſue) ſhall be found to have <hi>reall faith.</hi> It is our Lords warning to all, and it is a dreadfull one <hi>(Mat.</hi> 18. 6.) <hi>Who ſo ſhall offend one of theſe little ones, that beleeve in me, it were better for him, that a mil-ſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the ſea.</hi> A little one beleeving, or one beleeving though but a little (I mean little, in regard of the degree, not of the object) (I ſay, ſuch a little one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving) is a great one in the eye of Chriſt; an offence given to ſuch a ſcarce diſcernable beleever, may bring very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable wrath upon his offenders.</p>
            <p>And if Chriſt take it thus ill, when <hi>a little one</hi> beleeving in him is offended, will he not take it worſe, when <hi>a great one, an Abraham, a Stephen, a Paul</hi> in beleeving is offended? Where there is greateſt faith, there's greateſt worth, and tendereſt endearments to Jeſus Chriſt. When we ſee
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:158527:27"/> faith budding out and flouriſhing in noble and generous fruits of holineſſe, when faith hath ſo purified the heart, that it keeps hand and life pure, and acts viſibly; ſurely a mil-ſtone is not heavy enough, he ſhall have a mountain of mil-ſtones ſtrung together, for his neck, who knowingly and willingly offends ſuch a one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But whatſoever their faith is, they differ in opinion, and will not meet us in the ſame practice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Holy love, muſt and will bear much, where it ſees holy faith. <hi>Charity</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 7.) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves all things;</hi> I am ſure it beleeves this, <hi>That they who indeed beleeve in God, cannot continue to be hurtfull to any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men.</hi> And though I nothing doubt, but that a good man may do very ill, and may very juſtly ſuffer for it too; yet of how narrow a uſe are thoſe excellent graces of love, of meeknes, of humility, of patience, of ſelf-deniall, if they are not (among other uſes) to be laid out and beſtowed in a brotherly, hearty, gracious, amicable compliance with, bearing of, and condeſcention unto thoſe, <hi>who having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained like precious faith with us,</hi> do yet differ in ſome things which concerne order, they maintaining order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, and peace with others?</p>
            <p>I hope there is a good ſtock of charity yet among us, none of which ſhall be laviſht out in ſymbolizing with the ignorant and profane, or admitting them to a partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation in ſpeciall goſpel-priviledges; nor will it all (I am perſwaded) be laid out (though that is like to be coſtly to charity) in admitting thoſe of competent knowledge, and unblameable carriage in their lives, who yet evidence little (if any thing) of the life of faith: But (when the former charge is defrayed) charity will have a faire remainder in banke for thoſe (to whom it is very due) who are unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:158527:27"/> eminent and active in faith, though in ſome things they be found to differ in judgement, or in practices thereon depending.</p>
            <p>As to bear all differences would make charity blinde, ſo not to bear ſome would make her more then lame. I know <hi>(Honourable Senatours)</hi> your wiſedom will eaſily finde and diſcerne the <hi>limit-ſtone,</hi> between <hi>liberty,</hi> and <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertiniſme,</hi> between the <hi>humours of men, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How deſireable is it, that all the Churches ſhould have, as one minde, ſo one way, that they ſhould all minde and do the ſame thing? How pleaſant, how bleſſed a ſight were it, to behold not only <hi>unity of ſpirit,</hi> but <hi>uniformity of practice</hi> in all who call on the Name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, both their Lord and ours? But how wofull a ſight will it be, (if ever it ſhould be ſeen) that with whom we agree in every doctrine of faith, in the ſubſtance of worſhip and government, and in many formes; that from them we muſt irreconcileably break, till we can be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme? What a wofull dearth of Goſpel-love will be found amongſt us, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after all our former ſufferings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, our praying and faſting together, we ſhould upon theſe termes fall a vexing one another? If after we have poured forth our cries, our groanes, our ſighs, our tears together, in private chambers, and ſolemn aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies before the Lord; if after we have poured out our bloud together in the high places of the field before the enemy; if (I ſay) after all this, we ſhall on theſe termes, (I ſay not, cruelly poure out the bloud of one another, but ſo much as) unkindly move a cry, a groan, a ſigh, or draw a tear from one another, what a wofull dearth of Goſpel-love
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:158527:28"/> will be found amongſt us? Would it not alſo argue that there is ſome accurſed thing, ſome provocation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, if, after the Lord hath given us ſuch clear light to pull down the pillars of <hi>Babylon,</hi> he ſhould yet give us up to ſuch thick darkneſſe, that with our own hands we ſhould (upon ſuch diſſents) pull down any, who are pillars in <hi>Sion?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
